RG 005:027, Office of the Governor: Raymond E. Baldwin (1939-1941)
Connecticut State Library
Raymond E. Baldwin records
1939-1941
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Governor (1939-1941: Baldwin)
19.25 cubic feet
Gov. Raymond E. Baldwin's correspondence and subject files from his first administration.
RG005_027
Multiple
Biographical Note
Born: August 31, 1893, Rye, New York.
College: Wesleyan University, 1916; Yale Law School, 1921.
Political Party: Republican.
Offices: Stratford Town Court, Prosecutor, 1927-1930,
Stratford Town Court, Judge, 1931-1933,
Connecticut General Assembly, House, 1930-1935,
Governor of Connecticut, 1939-1941, 1943-1946,
US Senate, 1946-1949,
Associate Justice, Connecticut Supreme Court of Errors, 1949-1959,
Chief Justice, Connecticut Supreme Court of Errors, 1959-1963.
Died: October 4, 1986, Fairfield, Connecticut.
It had been more than 70 years since a Connecticut governor who was voted out of office successfully won it back at a later election. Beginning in 1938, Raymond Baldwin ran for the office in four consecutive elections and won three of them.
Although his ancestors had lived in Connecticut for many years, Baldwin was born just across the border in Rye, New York, the son of Lucian Earl and Sarah Emily (Tyler) Baldwin. The family moved to Middletown, Connecticut in 1901, where he attended Central Grammar School, graduated from Middletown High School in 1912, and graduated from Wesleyan University in 1916. He served in the US Navy during World War I, enlisting as a seaman. He was assigned to officer training school and in February 1918 was commissioned as an ensign at Annapolis. His war service was on a destroyer. Following the war, he received a law degree from Yale in 1921. Baldwin practiced law in New Haven and Bridgeport. On June 29, 1922 he married Edith Lindholm of Middletown, daughter of Andrew and Louisa Lindholm, a graduate of Connecticut College at New London and a teacher at Middletown High School. They had three children. Edith died in 1970.
In 1922, Baldwin was interviewed by Republican Party chairman, J. Henry Roraback, who designated him to be Governor Templeton's personal secretary. However, Baldwin angered the party boss by refusing to do so. He served as prosecutor of the Stratford Town Court from 1927-1930 and judge of the Stratford Town Court from 1931-1933. In 1930 he was elected to the General Assembly; in 1933 he became House Majority Leader and chairman of the Judiciary Committee.
When Roraback committed suicide in 1937, the Republican Party had no one who was able to replace him as the party's boss. Baldwin collaborated with others in the party who called themselves "New Republicans" and was nominated to run for governor as a reform candidate. His campaign was aided by the strong vote gained that year by the Socialist candidate, Jasper McLevy. Baldwin was also helped by the Union Party, a small third party that made him its candidate for governor. This party's 3,046 votes actually gave him the margin of victory he needed to defeat the popular four-term governor, Wilbur Cross. Baldwin won by 2,688 votes out of some 458,000 cast. He served one term and then lost his reelection bid to Robert Hurley during the nation-wide Democratic sweep of 1940. However, two years later he challenged Hurley and was once more elected governor. He was reelected in 1944.
As governor, Baldwin established compulsory annual audits of state and town books and was able to balance the state budget without seeking new taxes. He tended to support the needs of Connecticut businesses and did not like the increased role of the Federal government under the New Deal. However, he provided a more moderate approach to government than had the Republican administrations of the 1920's.
Baldwin's accomplishments as governor were prodigious. He supported more progressive labor legislation, including an anti-injunction bill, the redefinition of conspiracy laws, greater workers' compensation benefits, and the first comprehensive pension system for state employees. He supported efforts to employ more workers in Connecticut and established a job-training program to prepare workers for defense industry jobs. This program became a model for similar programs throughout the country. In 1943 he established the Inter-Racial Commission so that grievances of the state's African-American population might be heard. This commission is believed to be the first civil rights unit of its kind in the country. He also reformed the minor court system.
Two and a half years before the US entered World War II, Baldwin reorganized the state's Military Department. He also established the State Development Commission and the Aeronautical Development Commission, two agencies that helped convert Connecticut industry from peacetime output to defense and war production. During the war, the State Defense Council was recognized as one of the foremost in the country.
In 1944 Baldwin was elected to a third term. In 1945, there was a 150-day labor strike in Connecticut. Believing it threatened national security, he used troops to stop it. During this term a state labor relations act was passed, a Connecticut Veterans Advisory and Reemployment Commission established, and a program to help equalize educational opportunities was launched.
Baldwin had planned to retire from politics when his term ended in January of 1947, but in 1946 he was convinced by his party to run for the US Senate. In order to gain seniority over other freshman senators, Baldwin resigned as governor on December 27, 1946 and went to Washington to fill the remaining term of Senator Francis T. Maloney, who had died in early January 1945. The seat had been temporarily held by Admiral Thomas C. Hart, of Sharon, Connecticut. Baldwin's resignation allowed the Democratic lieutenant governor, Wilbert Snow, to serve 13 days as governor.
Raymond Baldwin had a presence on the national Republican stage. In 1940 he was a potential running mate for Wendell Wilkie but failed to gain the nomination. In 1944 he was spoken of as potential presidential candidate. He was the Connecticut "favorite son" presidential candidate at the 1948 Republican National Convention.
In 1949, Baldwin resigned from the Senate to accept appointment by Democratic Governor Chester Bowles to the Connecticut Supreme Court of Errors. He became its Chief Justice in 1959, thereby becoming only the second Connecticut person to have served as the state's governor, US Senator, and Chief Justice (the first was Jonathan Trumbull). As Chief Justice he oversaw a major reorganization of the state's court system. After he retired from the court in 1963, Baldwin continued to work in the justice system as a referee.
He was the chairman of Connecticut's Constitutional Convention of 1965, which rewrote the state's Constitution to conform to the US Supreme Court's one-man, one-vote ruling. Baldwin was a member of the Connecticut State Library Committee and its successor, the State Library Board, from 1957-1982 and served as its chair for many years. In tribute to his service, the board renamed the State Library's museum the Raymond E. Baldwin Museum of Connecticut History in 1983. The Baldwin Bridge that carries the Connecticut Turnpike (Rt. 95) from Old Lyme to Old Saybrook is also named for him. Baldwin was the first governor to use the Governor's Mansion located on Prospect Avenue in Hartford. Two homes he once owned, one in Stratford and one in Middletown, are in private hands.
Bibliography
Baldwin, Raymond E. Let's Go Into Politics. New York: Macmillan, 1952 [CSL call number JF 2051 .B24].
Boston Sunday Globe, October 5, 1986, p. 55.
Hartford Courant, October 5, 1986, p. 1.
Johnson, Curtiss S. Raymond E. Baldwin: Connecticut Statesman. Chester, Conn.: Pequot Press, 1972 [CSL call number F 100 .B3 J6].
New York Times, October 5, 1986, p. 44.
Sobel, Robert and John Raimo. Biographical Directory of the Governors of the United States, 1789-1978. Westport, Conn.: Meckler Books, 1978 [CSL call number GIS Ref E 176 .B573].
Scope and Content
Gov. Raymond E. Baldwin's records are correspondence and subject files related to state agencies, commissions, legislative bills, and appointments among other topics.
Arrangement
Series 1. Correspondence.
Series 2. Subject Files.
Related Material
RG 005:29, Records of the Governor, Gov. Raymond E. Baldwin, 1943-1946.
RG 006:38, Records of the Secretary of the State: Constitutional Convention of 1965.
RG 012, Records of the Connecticut State Library.
RG 040, Records of the Post-War Planning Board, 1943-1945.
RG 049, Records of the Veterans Advisory Commission, 1943-1949.
RG 050, Records of the State War Council, 1940-1945.
RG 069:10, Papers of Raymond E. Baldwin, 1938-1977. Includes records and manuscripts from his gubernatorial term up through his term as Supreme Court Justice and scrapbooks covering his entire career. Hundreds of photographs from the Baldwin family are housed with the Pictorial Archives.
Index Terms
Persons:
Baldwin, Raymond E. (Raymond Earl), 1893-1986
Subjects:
Baldwin, Raymond E. (Raymond Earl), 1893-1986 -- Archives; Connecticut. Office of the Governor -- Archives; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950 -- Sources; Governors -- Connecticut -- Archives
Document Types:
Correspondence; Records
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Correspondence, T001239
  - A-Com (Box 416)
  - Con-Q (Box 417)
  - R-U (Box 418)
  - W-Z (Box 419)
- Series 2. Subject Files
  - T001239
    - Accountancy, State Board of (Box 420)
    - Adjutant General (Box 420)
    - Aeronautical Development Commission (Box 420)
    - Aeronautics, Department of (Box 420)
    - Agricultural Experiment Station (Box 420)
    - Agriculture, Department of (Box 420)
    - American Legion (Box 420)
    - American Prison Association Conference (Box 420)
    - American Red Cross (Box 420)
    - American School for the Deaf (Box 420)
    - Architects, Board of Examiners of (Box 420)
    - Athletic Commission (Box 420)
    - Attorney General (Box 420)
    - Attorney General - Opinions (Box 420)
    - Auditor - State (Box 420)
    - Automobile Study (Box 420)
    - Bank Commission (Box 420)
    - Barbers’ Commission (Box 420)
    - Billboard Control (Box 421)
    - Bingo (Box 421)
    - Budget, Additions to (Box 421)
    - Budget Division (Box 421)
    - Budget Message, Comments on (Box 421)
    - Building Fund, State (Box 421)
    - Building Program, Additions to (Box 421)
    - Building Program - Proposed (Box 421)
    - Cedarcrest Sanitarium (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, Bridgeport (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, Connecticut (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, Hartford (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, Manchester (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, Meriden (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, New York State (Box 421)
    - Chamber of Commerce, United States (Box 421)
    - Chemist, State (Box 421)
    - Cheshire Academy (Box 421)
    - Chiropody, Board of Examiners in (Box 421)
    - Chiropractic - Board of Examiners (Box 421)
    - Civil Engineers, Connecticut, Board of (Box 421)
    - Civil Service (Box 421)
    - Compensation Commissioners (Box 421)
    - Comptroller (Box 421)
    - Compulsory Auto Insurance (Box 421)
    - Conference on Social and Labor Legislation (Box 421)
    - Conference on State Defense (Box 421)
    - Congratulations (Box 422)
    - Conn. Council for National Defense (Box 422)
    - Conn. Development Commission (Box 422)
    - Conn. Humane Society (Box 422)
    - Conn. Industrial Open House Weekend (Box 422)
    - Conn. League of Municipalities (Box 422)
    - Conn. Marketing Authority (Box 422)
    - Conn. Medical Society (Box 422)
    - Conn. Prison Association (Box 422)
    - Conn. Reformatory (Box 422)
    - Conn. School for Boys (Box 422)
    - Conn. Society of Civil Engineers (Box 422)
    - Conn. Society of Professional Engineers (Box 422)
    - Conn. State Apprenticeship Council (Box 422)
    - Conn. State Farm for Women (Box 422)
    - Conn. State Hospital (Box 422)
    - Conn. State Prison (Box 422)
    - Contingent [contingency] Fund (Box 422)
    - Council of State Governments (Box 422)
    - County Commissioners (Box 422)
    - Court System (Box 422)
    - Daily Cash Balances [empty] (Box 423)
    - Dairy and Food Commission (Box 423)
    - Danbury Penal Institute (Proposed) (Box 423)
    - Dental Commission (Box 423)
    - Domestic Animals Commission (Box 423)
    - Dual - Job Holding (Box 423)
    - Eastern States Exposition (Box 423)
    - Education (Box 423)
    - Education - (Committee on Education Program) (Box 423)
    - Education of the Blind, Dept. of (Box 423)
    - Election Law Committee (Box 423)
    - Embalmers, Board of Examiners of (Box 423)
    - Employment Problems of Negro, Commission to Study (Box 423)
    - Employment Service (Box 423)
    - Engineers and Land Surveyors, State Board of Registration for Professional (Box 423)
    - Fairfield State Hospital (Box 423)
    - Farm Activities, Coordination of, at State Institutions (Box 423)
    - Finance and Control, Board of (Box 423)
    - Fish and Game Commission (Box 424)
    - Flood Control (Box 424)
    - Fund Operations, Monthly Reports of (Box 424)
    - Gambling (Box 424)
    - General Assembly - Messages to (Box 424)
    - Geological & Natural History Survey Commission (Box 424)
    - Groton - New London Bridge Commission (Box 424)
    - Hairdressers & Cosmeticians Commission (Box 424)
    - Harbormasters (Box 424)
    - Hartford Bridge Commission (Box 424)
    - Hartford County Jail (Box 424)
    - Healing Arts, Board of (Box 424)
    - Health, State Depart[ment] of (Box 424)
    - Highway Department-1939 (Box 424)
    - Highway Department - 1940 (Box 425)
    - Highway Safety Commission - 1939 (Box 425)
    - Highway Safety Commission - 1940 (Box 425)
    - Highway Safety Dinners (Box 425)
    - Homeopathic Examining Board (Box 425)
    - Hospital Districts, State Board on (Box 425)
    - Hospital Service Plan (Box 425)
    - Housing (Box 425)
    - Inaugural Address (Box 425)
    - Inaugural Ball - 1939 (Box 425)
    - Insurance Commissioner (Box 425)
    - Intergovernmental Cooperation, Governor's Committee on (Box 426)
    - International Affairs (Box 426)
    - Job Training (Box 426)
    - Joint Executive Defense Committee (Box 426)
    - Judicial Council (Box 426)
    - Juvenile Court (Box 426)
    - Labor Board (Box 426)
    - Labor Department (Box 426)
    - Laurel Heights (Box 426)
    - Leesville Dam (Box 426)
    - Legislative Commission on Jails (Box 426)
    - Legislative Council (Box 427)
    - Library, State (Box 427)
    - Liquor Control Commission (Box 427)
    - Long Lane Farm (Box 427)
    - Man - Marketing Clinic (Box 427)
    - Mansfield State Training School (Box 427)
    - Mediation and Arbitration, Board of (Box 427)
    - Medical Examining Board (Box 427)
    - Mental Defectives, Commission to Build New School for (Box 427)
    - Merritt Parkway (Box 427)
    - Milk Administration (Box 427)
    - Minor Courts (Box 427)
    - Mosquito Control (Box 427)
    - Motor Vehicle Inspection (Box 427)
    - Motor Vehicles (Box 428)
    - Mystic Oral School for the Deaf (Box 428)
    - National Defense (Box 428)
    - National Guard (Box 428)
    - National Resources Committee (Box 428)
    - Naturopathic Examiners (Box 428)
    - Neutrality (Box 428)
    - New England Council (Box 428)
    - New England Railway Commission (Box 428)
    - New Haven County Jail (Box 428)
    - New Haven Harbor (Box 428)
    - New Haven Water Company (Box 428)
    - Newington Home (Box 428)
    - Norwich Investigation (Box 428)
    - Norwich State Hospital (Box 428)
    - Notary Public (Box 429)
    - Nurses - Board of Examination and Registration (Box 429)
    - Opticians (Box 429)
    - Optometry, State Board of Examiners in (Box 429)
    - Osteopathy, Registration and Examination Board of (Box 429)
    - Pardons, Board of (Box 429)
    - Park and Forest Commission (Box 429)
    - Personnel (Box 429)
    - Personnel Advisory Committee (Box 429)
    - Pharmacy (Box 429)
    - Police, State (Box 429)
    - Proposed Legislation (Box 430)
    - Protests on Senate Bill 201 (Box 430)
    - Public Administration Service (Box 430)
    - Public Buildings Administration (Federal - Post Offices) (Box 430)
    - Public Utilities Commission (Box 430)
    - Public Welfare Council (Box 430)
    - Public Works Department (Box 430)
    - Publicity Department (Box 431)
    - Purchases, Supervisor of (Box 431)
    - Reemployment, Advisory Council on (Box 431)
    - Regional Market (Box 431)
    - Representatives (Box 431)
    - Requisitions (Box 431)
    - Retirement Plan, State Employees’ (Box 431)
    - Rivers, Harbors, and Bridges Commission (Box 431)
    - Sculpture, Commission of (Box 431)
    - Secretary of State (Box 431)
    - Selective Service Boards (Box 431)
    - Senators (Box 431)
    - Shell Fish Commission (Box 431)
    - Social Security Board (Box 431)
    - Southbury Training School - Report (Box 431)
    - Standardization Committee (Box 431)
    - State Bonds (Box 431)
    - State Defense (Offer of Services) (Box 431)
    - State Hospitals (Box 431)
    - State Income Tax (Box 431)
    - State Rehabilitation Committee (Box 431)
    - State’s Attorneys (Box 431)
    - Statute Revision Commissioner (Box 431)
    - Steamship Terminals, Commission on (Box 431)
    - Suggestions - Signing of Bills (Box 431)
    - Tax Department (Box 431)
    - Tax Receipts (Box 432)
    - Teachers’ Colleges (Box 432)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 432)
    - Toll - Bridges and Highways (Box 432)
    - Trade Schools (Box 432)
    - Traffic Commission (State) (Box 432)
    - Treasurer (Box 432)
    - Treatment and Care of People Afflicted with Physical or Mental Disabilities, Commission on (Box 432)
    - Tree Protection Examining Board (Box 432)
    - Tuberculosis Commission (Box 432)
    - Uncas – on - Thames (Box 432)
    - Undercliff Sanatorium (Box 432)
    - Unemployment Compensation Advisory Council (Box 432)
    - Unemployment Compensation Com. (Box 432)
    - Unemployment Compensation Commissioners (Box 432)
    - Unemployment Compensation Law (Box 432)
    - University of Connecticut (Box 432)
    - V – Inclusive Miscellaneous (Box 433)
    - Veterans Home Commission (Box 433)
    - Veterans Hospital Newington (Box 433)
    - Veterinary Examining Board (Box 433)
    - Veto Suggestions (Box 433)
    - War Department (Box 433)
    - Water Commission (Box 433)
    - Welfare Department - 1939 (Box 433)
    - Welfare Department - 1940 (Box 433)
    - Western Trip (Box 433)
    - World’s Poultry Congress (Box 433)
    - WPA (Box 433)
    - Yale University (Box 434)
    - Youth, Connecticut Conference of (Box 434)
  - 2003-012
    - Booklet related to the printing industry. (Box 1)